Guide to the United Women Firefighters Records and Photographs WAG.057
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
- Series III: Organizational Files, 1977-2002
  - Subseries B: Women in Fire Suppression/Fire Service, 1983-1999
    The WFS is a national organization of women in firefighting, founded in 1982 by firefighters Terese Floren and Linda Willing. Brenda Berkman served as a trustee of the WFS from 1983 to 1992. The WFS publishes a newsletter, Firework. The series includes correspondence, materials related to the regional and national conferences on women in firefighting sponsored by the WFS, transcriptions of interviews with Brenda Berkman from a 1987-1988 oral history project, membership, and organizational materials.
    - Articles of Incorporation, 1983 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - By-Laws, 1990-1991 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Clippings, 1986-1999 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Committees, 1991-1992 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Conferences, Regional, Madison WI, 1986 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Conferences, First National, Boulder, CO, 1985 (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - Conferences, Second National, Seattle, WA, 1987 (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - Conferences, Third National, Asheville, NC, 1989 (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - Conferences, Fourth National, San Diego, CA, 1991 (Box 8, Folder 16)
    - Conferences, Fifth National, Rockford, IL, 1993 (Box 8, Folder 17)
    - Conferences, Other Organizations, 1988-1991 (Box 8, Folder 18)
    - Correspondence, 1983 (Box 8, Folder 19)
    - Correspondence, 1987 (Box 8, Folder 20)
    - Correspondence, 1988 (Box 8, Folder 21)
    - Correspondence, 1989 (Box 8, Folder 22)
    - Correspondence, 1990 (Box 8, Folder 23)
    - Correspondence, Jan 1991-Jun 1991 (Box 8, Folder 24)
    - Correspondence, Jul 1991-Dec 1991 (Box 8, Folder 25)
    - Correspondence, Jan 1992-Jun 1992 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, Jul 1992-Dec 1992 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, Jan 1993-Jun 1993 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, Jul 1993-Dec 1993 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, 1994 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence, 1995 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence, 1996 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence, 1998 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence, 1999 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Financial, 1989-1994 (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - History, 1980-1991 (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - Membership, 1991-1993 (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - Minutes, Trustees Meetings, 1989-1995 (Box 9, Folder 13)
    - Oral History Project: Interviews with Brenda Berkman (2) and Terese Floren, 1987-1988 (Box 9, Folder 14)
    - Policies, 1984-1991 (Box 9, Folder 15)
    - Publications, Handbook on Women in Fire Fighting, 1992 (Box 9, Folder 16)
    - Survey of Women Firefighters, undated (Box 9, Folder 17)
    - Trustees, 1983-1995 (Box 9, Folder 18)
- Series IV: Photographs and Memorabilia, circa 1980-1999
  Series consists of approximately one hundred black-and-white and color prints of various sizes, nineteen color slides, a small amount of negatives, and one black-and-white contact sheet, with portraits, event and documentary photographs from circa 1980 to 1999. Also includes a small amount of artifacts and memorabilia from Brenda Berkman's career as a firefighter including badges, membership cards, a UWF pin, FDNY calendars, and ephemera related to Berkman's termination in 1983.
  Photographs include a 5x7 black-and-white print and corresponding 4x5 negative of Berkman in FDNY uniform; black-and-white prints, and color prints and negatives, from a City Council Press Conference on July 19, 1992; 4x6 color prints from a Women's Action Coalition Demonstration against FDNY sexual harrassment on September 10, 1992; and 8x10 black-and-white prints including Brenda Berkman speaking at a press conference with city officials, of Women Tell the Truth: A Conference on Parity, Power and Sexual Harrassment on April 25th, 1992 at Hunter College, including Anita Hill and Gloria Steinem, and of Berkman and Comptroller Elizabeth Holtzman. Two large color group portraits of women firefighters include the Fourth National Conference of Fire Service Women in San Diego in 1991.
  Nineteen color slides, mostly from 1982, include images of the first women firefighters training for their physical exam in 1982, including at the Fire Academy on Randall's Island; candidate Katrina Cannon taking the oath of office in 1982 as a probationary firefighter, representing the first group; portraits of Brenda Berkman and attorney Robert King; as well as a group portrait, circa 1988, of the first women firefighters of New York City.
  - Artifacts and Memorabilia [Includes Membership Cards, Badges, Pin, Ephemera], 1982-1983, undated (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Booklet ["The Role of Women in the Fire Service," FEMA], Aug 1980 (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence [Includes Letter from Brenda Berkman Identifying People in Some Photographs], 1990, 1993 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Brenda Berkman, Photographs of [Includes Women's History Night, Two Portraits], 1987, 1993, undated (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Calendars [UFA FDNY and UFO ASSN], 1983-1985 (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - City Council Press Conference Photographs, July 19, 1992 (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - Group Portraits of Women Firefighters (Oversized) [Includes Fourth National Conference of Fire Service Women, San Diego, 1991], 1991, undated (Box X0S002)
  - Portrait of Brenda Berkman, First Woman Firefighter of New York City (Permission Required to Reproduce) [4x5 Negative], undated (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - Slides [Includes Group Portraits and Photographs of First Women Firefighters of New York City], circa 1980-1989 (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - United Women Firefighters, Assorted Photos, "Women Tell the Truth," and others, 1992 (Box 16, Folder 9)
  - United Women Firefighters, Various Color Photos, 1999, undated (Box 16, Folder 10)
  - Women's Action Coalition Demonstration Photographs, Sep 10, 1992 (Box 16, Folder 11)
- Series V: Unprocessed Materials, 1957-2011
  - September 11, 2001 attacks, FDNY recruitment, and the closing of Engine 204, circa 1998-2003 (Box 10)
  - Brenda Berkman Papers: Promotion to Lieutenant, 1996-1997 White House Fellow, and the Candidate Physical Abilities Test (CPAT), circa 1957-2003 (Box 11)
  - Brenda Berkman Papers: 9/11 Materials, including Correspondence to Berkman and Student Artwork, News Articles, and Programs for Events Honoring Women of 9/11, early 1990s, 2011 (Box 12)
  - Videos, 1980s-2000s (Box 13-15)